Guide to the Harold F. Gosnell Papers 1886-1997
University of Chicago Library
Gosnell, Harold F. Papers
1886-1997
70 linear feet (140 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Harold Foote Gosnell (1896-1997) was a political scientist at the University of Chicago during the 1920s and 1930s. He also worked for the federal government and spent the latter part of his academic career at American and Howard Universities. He was renowned for his work on voter behavior, particularly with reference to African-American politics and Chicago politics. The Harold F. Gosnell Papers contain correspondence, teaching materials, writings, and research files spanning 1886-1997.
Information on Use
Access
Series IX contains students grades restricted for 80 years. The remainder of the collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Harold Foote Gosnell (1896-1997) grew up in Rochester, New York, where he attended the University and graduated in 1918. He served briefly in the army, remaining in America, before pursuing graduate studies in political science at the University of Chicago. At Chicago Gosnell worked with Charles E. Merriam, graduating in 1922 and staying on as faculty. By 1932 Gosnell was an Associate Professor and closely associated with Merriam's approach to the discipline, which incorporated methods from economics, sociology, and psychology.
Gosnell's work during the 1920s and 1930s used statistical analyses to draw conclusions about voter behavior and political participation. He became known for his research into Chicago politics and the African-American vote; Negro Politicians: The Rise of Negro Politics and Chicago (1935) and Machine Politics: The Chicago Model (1937) were still considered authoritative texts in the 1990s. Gosnell also completed studies of American non-voters and voter turnout in Europe. His work was consistently valued for its "behaviorism" method, which made use of the quantitative models favored by the other social sciences, but modified their tendency towards determinism.
Despite this success, however, the Political Science Department came under increasing criticism from University President Robert Hutchins, who disliked Charles Merriam's political activism. In 1941 Gosnell accepted a job with the Bureau of the Budget. In 1946 he moved to the State Department, where he remained until 1960. He continued to publish on voter motivations, though his case studies of presidential leadership demonstrated a shift away from behaviorism.
During this period Gosnell also served as faculty at American University, where he conducted research on the Soviet Union for their Special Operations Research Office. In 1962 he was invited to teach at Howard University, where his scholarship on African-American politics was particularly admired. Gosnell retired in 1970, but continued to receive accolades for his contribution to the discipline, awarded the Charles E. Merriam Award from the American Political Science Association in 1981. Both APSA and the University of Rochester created fellowships named for him, and by the time of his death in 1997 Gosnell was widely considered to have made quantitative analysis mainstream in political science.
Gosnell was married to Florence Fake, who died in 1991.
Scope Note
The Harold F. Gosnell Papers are organized into nine series:
Series I: Personal and Biographical, contains artwork, address books, clippings, finances, memorabilia, and photos. It includes a draft of Gosnell's autobiography. Material spans 1886-1972 and is organized by subject.
Series II: Correspondence, contains Gosnell's professional, family, and personal correspondence. It is organized alphabetically and spans 1919-1997.
Series III: Academic Administration and Teaching, contains administrative reports, examinations, lectures, student work, and syllabi from Gosnell's time at the University of Chicago (1926-1941), American University (1946-1962), and Howard University (1962-1970). Graded student work and letters of recommendation have been restricted transferred to Series IX. Oversized material has been transferred to Series VIII.
Series IV: Writings, contains books, articles, and reviews written by Gosnell and others. Material is organized by title and by author, and spans 1921-1977.
Series V: Government Work, contains interviews, memoranda, press releases, and reports from Gosnell's work at the Bureau of the Budget and the Department of State, 1941-1960. This series is organized by department.
Series VI: Professional Activities, contains newsletters and correspondence from organizations to which Gosnell belonged. It is arranged by name and spans 1951-1990.
Series VII: Research Files, contains charts, clippings, interviews, memorabilia, newsletters, notes, publications, polls, propaganda, and surveys related to Gosnell's research on public policy and political theory. Oversized material has been transferred to Series VIII. This series is organized by topic and spans the 1910s through the 1970s.
Series VIII: Oversized, contains books, clippings, graphs, electoral maps, and campaigns posters, primarily related to American and British elections. Material has been transferred from Series III and VII. It spans 1922-1940.
Series IX: Restricted, contains graded student work and letters of recommendation.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
Browse finding aids by topic.
Merriam, Charles E. Papers
University of Chicago. Department of Political Science. Records
Subject Headings
Gosnell, Harold Foote, 1896-;; Howard University; American University (Washington, D.C.). Special Operations Research Office; United States. Bureau of the Budget; United States. Dept. of State; University of Chicago. Political Science Dept.; African Americans -- Politics and government; Chicago (Ill.) -- Politics and government; Elections; Political parties; Political science; Political scientists; Voting
INVENTORY
- Series I: Personal and Biographical
  This series contains artwork, address books, clippings, finances, memorabilia, and photos. It includes a draft of Gosnell's autobiography. Material spans 1886-1972 and is organized by subject.
  - Address books, 1915-1948 (Box 1)
  - Address books, 1949-1979 (Box 2)
  - Art, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Autobiography, notes, 1917-1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Autobiography, undated (Box 3, Folder 3-13)
  - Autobiography, undated (Box 4, Folder 1-22)
  - Autobiography, undated (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Bibliography, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Biographical files, undated (Box 5, Folder 4-7)
  - Charles E. Merriam Award, speech, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Child care, pamphlets, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Christmas cards, 1950s-1970s (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Christmas decorations, guide, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Dinner in Gosnell's honour, speech, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Elementary school, attendance records, 1909-1910 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Fiftieth Anniversary, party plans, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Fake, Florence, speech, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Gosnell, Florence Fake ("Bonnie"), papers, circa 1980s (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Gosnell, Charles, clippings, 1960s (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Gosnell, Harold, clippings, circa 1930s (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Gosnell, James, signature, 1886 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Graduate school, applications, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Health, clippings, 1930s (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - High school, memorabilia, 1906-1914 (Box 5, Folder 22-23)
  - High school, debating speeches, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Houses, floor plans, circa 1930s (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Insurance, 1980s (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Kiplinger Magazine, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Memorabilia, undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Military service, records, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Model airplanes, guides, 1940s (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Model boats, guides, undated (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
  - Mountain School, VT, information, 1980s (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper clippings, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 6, Folder 5-7)
  - Newspaper comic, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Oldsmobile F-85, maintenance records, 1960s (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Passports, 1920s-1950s (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Photos and postcards, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Portraits, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Principia, session schedules and drawings, 1970s (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
  - Psi Upsilon, memorabilia, 1920s-1930s (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Religion, pamphlets, 1930s (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Roloc slides, order forms, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Sketches, undated (Box 7, Folder 7-8)
  - Stocks, 1960s (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Student memorabilia, 1920s (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Suburban Hospital, narrative of stay, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Travel, 1950s-1974, undated (Box 7, Folder 12-16)
  - Truman, Harry, photos, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - UNICEF, pamphlet, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - University of Rochester, photos and alumni information, 1918-1980s (Box 8, Folder 3-6)
  - Wills, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Window screens, manual, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Series II: Correspondence
  This series contains Gosnell's professional, family, and personal correspondence. It is divided into three subseries:
  Subseries 1: Professional Correspondence, contains correspondence from publishers and academic colleagues. It is organized by name or topic and spans 1920-1987.
  Subseries 2: Family Correspondence, contains correspondence between Gosnell and his family, primarily his mother, Sylvia Foote Gosnell, and his wife, Florence Fake Gosnell ("Bonnie"). It includes letters of condolence sent to Gosnell's son, David, on Gosnell's death in 1997. Of note is a Civil War letter from Gosnell's grandfather, Lemuel Foote, enclosed in Sylvia Gosnell's letter of 25 August 1935. It is organized alphabetically and spans 1919-1997.
  Subseries 3: Personal Correspondence, contains incoming and outgoing correspondence between Gosnell and his friends and acquaintances. It is organized alphabetically and spans1919-1986.
  - Subseries 1: Professional Correspondence
    - A, 1940-1942 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - American Book Company, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - American Funds Group, 1980s (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - B, 1941-1954 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Benton, Bill, and C. Chester, 1942 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Birkhead Political Science Award, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Bulmer, Martin, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - C, 1935-1964 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Casey, Ralph D., 1930-1931 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Charles E. Merrill Publishers, 1972-1980s (Box 8, Folder 18-19)
    - El Colegio de Mexico, 1944-1945 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Comparative government, 1930-1938 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Congressional Quarterly, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Cromwell Company, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - D, 1932-1966 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - DeGrazia, Alfred, 1941-1942, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 6-8)
    - Disenfranchisement, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Education, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - F, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - G, 1940-1960 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - General, 1937-1948, 1969-1980 (Box 9, Folder 13-17)
    - Greenstein, Fred, 1978-1983 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Greenwood Press, 1979-1983 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - H, 1940-1980 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Harvard University Press, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Jacobs, Walter Darnell, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Johnson Reprint Corporation, 1976-1980 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - K, 1924-1952 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Karl, Berry D., 1966-1977 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - L, 1947-1957 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Lawyers' Cooperative Publishing Company, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - M, 1940-1966 (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Machine politics, 1948-1968 (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
    - Macmillan, 1946-1955 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Merriam, Charles E., 1926-1947 (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
    - N, 1936-1952 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Oxford University Press, 1946 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - P, 1947-1987 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Peel, Roy 1932-1934 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Platt, 1924 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Political parties, 1941-2 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Quiz Kids, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Riker, William, 1980-1983 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Ronald Press, 1946-1959 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Roosevelt, 1941 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Russell and Russell Publishers, 1968-1979 (Box 10, Folder 17-18)
    - S, 1942-1958 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Schuman, Fredrick, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Smolka, 1969-1974 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Strong, Esther B., 1965 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Swihart, James, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - T, 1931-1947 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - U, 1947-1976 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - University of Akron, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - University of Chicago, 1920, 1941-1942 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - University of Chicago Press, 1966-1969, 1970-1980 (Box 11, Folder 8-9)
    - University Microfilms, 1965-1982 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - University Presses, 1970s (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - University of Washington, 1954-1955 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - W, 1947 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Walton, Hanes, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Y, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Yates, 1979 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Z, 1941 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Unidentified, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Subseries 2: Family Correspondence
    - Fake family, 1926-1935 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Gosnell family, 1921-1935 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Gosnell, Arthur 1919-1946 (Box 11, Folder 21-22)
    - Gosnell, David, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - Gosnell, Florence Fake, 1926-1954, undated (Box 12, Folder 1-27)
    - Gosnell, Frank L., 1919-1948 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
    - Gosnell, Ralph Whitney, 1919-1980 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Gosnell, Sylvia Foote, 1919-1935 (Box 13, Folder 4-25)
    - Gosnell, Syvia Foote, 1935-1937 (Box 14, Folder 1-11)
  - Subseries 3: Personal Correspondence
    - Christmas letters, 1955-1957 (Box 14, Folder 12-13)
    - Cohen, Morris H., 1941-1943 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Ford, Lavery, 1941-1954 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Friends, 1947-1982 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - General, 1919-1958 (Box 14, Folder 17-18)
    - General, 1942-1972 (Box 15, Folder 1-9)
    - General, 1973-1986 (Box 16, Folder 1-6)
    - Tinker, Irene, and Janet Brown, 1963-1968 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Tuckers, 1960-1964 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Unidentified, undates (Box 17, Folder 1-2)
    - Wilson, Raymond W., 1977-1983 (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Series III: Academic Administration and Teaching
  This series contains administrative reports, examinations, lectures, student work, and syllabi. Graded student work and letters of recommendation have been transferred to Series IX. Series III is divided into two subseries:
  Subseries 1: University of Chicago, 1926-1941 contains materials dating from Gosnell's time as a professor in the Political Science Department.
  Subseries 2: Other Universities, 1946-1970, primarily contains materials dating from Gosnell's tenure at American University (1946-1962) and Howard University (1962-1970). Of note are the "political autobiographies" written by students for Gosnell's class on "Party Systems and Electoral Problems" at Howard University. This series includes syllabi from universities Gosnell was not affiliated with. Oversized material has been transferred to Series VIII.
  - Subseries 1: University of Chicago, 1926-1941
    - Announcements, Alumni Association (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - "Annual Report of the Political Science Department 1936" (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Catalogues, University of Chicago libraries (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Class charts (Box 17, Folder 7-8)
    - Clippings, Hutchins and the "Great Books" (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Course materials, "Nationalism," and "The Origin of the State" (Box 17, Folder 10-17)
    - Course materials, "Comparative Government" (Box 17, Folder 18-19)
    - Course materials, "Introduction to Political Parties" (Box 17, Folder 20-21)
    - Course materials, "Introduction to Political Parties" (Box 18, Folder 1-6)
    - Course materials, "The Electorate" (Box 18, Folder 7-10)
    - Course materials, "The Electorate" (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Course materials, "Comparative Political Parties" (Box 19, Folder 2-4)
    - Course materials, "International Law" (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Dissertation abstracts (Box 19, Folder 6-8)
    - Exams, B.A. (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Exams, comprehensive (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Exams, Division of the Social Sciences (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Exams, "European Government" (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - Exam, French (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - Exams, Ph.D. (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - Exams, politics (Box 19, Folder 15)
    - Fundraising, alumni (Box 19, Folder 16)
    - Inquiry, Senate Committee on Research (Box 19, Folder 17)
    - Lecture, Karl J. Holzinger (Box 19, Folder 18)
    - Lecture, Barry Karl (Box 19, Folder 19)
    - Lecture, Charles E. Merriam (Box 19, Folder 20)
    - Lecture, Social Sciences Division (Box 19, Folder 21)
    - Lecture, Social Sciences Division (Box 20, Folder 1-2)
    - Memoranda, Political Science Department (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Memorial, Harold Dwight Lasswell (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Memorial fund, Leonard White and Charles Merriam (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Minutes, Social Science Research Committee (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Obituary, Harold Dwight Lasswell (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Obituary, Charles E. Merriam (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Proposal, Social Science Research Committee (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - "Pulse Magazine" (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Requirements, Department of Education (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Requirements, Social Sciences Division (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - Responses to Hutchins' 2 year B.A. (Box 20, Folder 13)
    - Resume, Hymen Ezra Cohen (Box 20, Folder 14)
    - Syllabus, "American State and Local Government" (Box 20, Folder 15)
    - Syllabus, "Contemporary Society" (Box 20, Folder 16)
    - Term papers, American politics (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
    - Term papers, European politics (Box 21, Folder 3-5)
    - Term papers, law (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Term papers, political method (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 2: Other Universities, 1946-1970
    - American University, correspondence (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - American University, course materials, "Comparative Political Parties" (Box 22, Folder 2-5)
    - American University, course materials, "Political Parties and Electoral Problems" (Box 22, Folder 6-10)
    - American University, course material, "Political Parties and Pressure Groups" (Box 22, Folder 11-12)
    - American University, course materials, "Political Parties" (Box 22, Folder 13-14)
    - American University, course materials, "Public Opinion Measurement" (Box 22, Folder 15-17)
    - American University, course materials, "Public Opinion Measurement" (Box 23, Folder 1-2)
    - American University, dissertation abstracts (Box 23, Folder 3-4)
    - American University, lectures and research, Special Operations Research Office (Box 23, Folder 5-6)
    - American University, memoranda, School of Social Services (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - American University, reports, Social Science Research Committee (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - American University, research questionnaire (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - Columbia University, syllabi (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - Howard University, applications for stipends (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - Howard University, conference papers (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - Howard University, course materials, "American Leaders and Followers" (Box 23, Folder 13)
    - Howard University, course materials, "Directed Research" (Box 23, Folder 14-15)
    - Howard University, course materials, "Introduction to Political Communication" (Box 23, Folder 16)
    - Howard University, course materials, "Introduction to Political Communication" (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Howard University, course materials, "State and Local Government" (Box 24, Folder 2-4)
    - Howard University, course materials, "Party Systems" (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Howard University, course materials, "Comparative Political Parties" (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Howard University, course materials, "Party Systems and Electoral Problems" (Box 24, Folder 7-16)
    - Howard University, course materials, "Party Systems and Electoral Problems" (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Howard University, course materials, "Public Opinion" (Box 25, Folder 2-4)
    - Howard University, course materials, "Political Leadership" (Box 25, Folder 5-10)
    - Howard University, course materials, "The United Nations and its Role" (Box 25, Folder 11)
    - Howard University, degree requirements, government majors (Box 25, Folder 12)
    - Howard University, degree requirements, PhD (Box 25, Folder 13)
    - Howard University, lectures, Sydney Boas (Box 25, Folder 14)
    - Howard University, letter to faculty (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Howard University, memoranda, Political Science Department (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Howard University, "Negro Student Questionnaire" (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Howard University, obituary, Bernard Ball (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Howard University, student thesis proposals (Box 26, Folder 5-6)
    - Howard University, syllabi (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Howard University, term papers, federal grants and aid (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - Other universities, courses offered in politics and government (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - University of Rochester, lecture notes (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - University of Southern California, course materials, "Public Administration" (Box 26, Folder 11)
- Series IV: Writings
  This series contains books, articles, and reviews written by Gosnell and others. It is divided into three subseries:
  Subseries I: Books, contains drafts, outlines, notes, research material, and correspondence for books by Gosnell. Material is organized by title and spans 1922-1983. American Parties and Elections and American Party Leaders and Followers appear to be early versions of Political Parties and the American Creed. There are two distinct drafts of Political Parties and the American Creed. Democracy Makes a Difference and Democracy: The Threshold of Freedom are also related drafts.
  Subseries 2: Articles and Other Writings, contains articles and book reviews by Gosnell. These consist of both drafts and offprints, and in some cases related correspondence. Material is organized by title and spans 1921-1971.
  Subseries 3: Writings by Others, contains books and articles written by others. Materials is organized by author and spans the 1920s-1977.
  - Subseries 1: Books
    - American Parties and Elections -- Typescript and Photocopied Typescript, undated (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - American Parties and Elections -- Photocopied Typescript, undated (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - American Parties and Elections -- Photocopied Typescript, undated (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - American Parties and Elections -- Photocopied Typescript and Research, 1971-1972 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - American Parties and Elections -- Newsletters, 1979-1985 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - American Parties and Elections -- Clippings, Newsletters, Articles, 1977-1987 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - American Parties and Elections -- Clipping, 1977 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - American Parties and Elections -- Clippings and Newsletters, 1975-1983 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - American Parties and Elections -- Advertisement and Clippings, 1979 (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - American Parties and Elections -- Clipping, Campaigning Reports, 1979 (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - American Parties and Elections -- Clipping, Advertisements, 1980-1983 (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - American Parties and Elections -- Clipping, Correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - American Parties and Elections -- Newsletter and Report, 1982-1985 (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - American Parties and Elections -- Typescript, undated (Box 27, Folder 14)